Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- [And there a hunter's camp], about 1860; duk.00271; xxx.00114; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side are two lines, heavily corrected, from a draft of the poem first published in 1860 as Chants Democratic 4 and eventually titled Our Old Feuillage. On the other side are two lightly corrected lines with an uncertain connection to Whitman's published poetry. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [(written for the voice)], [Poem of "(the Devil], and Poem of Sadness.
- [(written for the voice)], about 1860; duk.00272; xxx.00041; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript note apparently recording the poet's early idea for the poem first published as Chants Democratic 20 in 1860, later as I Hear America Singing. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [And there a hunter's camp], [Poem of "(the Devil], and Poem of Sadness.
- [Poem of "(the Devil], 1865 or before; duk.00273; xxx.00005; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This note for a poem about the devil is possibly related to the poem Chanting the Square Deific, which was first published in 1865. The scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [And there a hunter's camp], [(written for the voice)], and Poem of Sadness.
- Poem of Sadness, about 1860; duk.00274; xxx.00153; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript note probably recording the idea for the 1860 poem Leaves of Grass 17, which was ultimately titled I Sit and Look Out. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [And there a hunter's camp], [(written for the voice)], and [Poem of "(the Devil]. An image of the verso is not available.
- [And there, farther south], 1855–1892; duk.00275; xxx.00110; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Fragment describing a "negro at daylight" giving "the Carolina yell," possibly related to the poem first published in 1856 as Poem of Salutation and later titled Salut Au Monde! This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with The Scout, Drops of my Blood, and [In a poem make the thought].
- "The Scout", about 1855 or later; duk.00276; xxx.00624; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript suggesting "The Scout" as a good title for a poem, magazine, or newspaper, of which the connection to Whitman's published work is unknown. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [And there, farther south], Drops of my Blood, and [In a poem make the thought].
- Drops of my Blood, about 1860; duk.00277; xxx.00084; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side is a list of trial titles, probably for the poem first published as Calamus 15 in Leaves of Grass ( 1860 ) and eventually titled Trickle Drops. On the reverse is a fragment of about two and a half lines, heavily corrected, whose relationship to Whitman's published poetry is unknown. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [And there, farther south], The Scout, and [In a poem make the thought].
- [In a poem make the thought], 1860 or before; duk.00278; xxx.00079; MS 4to 29; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Note for a poem to address the question "What will be the result of this years hence?" Possibly related to the poem Recorders Ages Hence, first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860 ) as Calamus 10, and taking its final title in 1867. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [And there, farther south], The Scout, and Drops of my Blood.
- [Poems identifying the different branches of the sciences], about 1859; duk.00072; xxx.00625; MS 4to 30; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  List of ideas for poems about astronomy, geology, chemistry, mathematics, and music. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- The Body—, 1850–1892; duk.00250; xxx.00626; MS 4to 30; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript containing ideas for a poem about the body as something more than physical. An image for the verso is unavailable.
- Poem of Language, 1860 or before; duk.00251; xxx.00627; MS 4to 30; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript containing ideas for a poem about the variety of languages and sounds. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Whole Poem]. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [Whole Poem], about 1855; duk.00252; xxx.00628; MS 4to 30; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript containing ideas for a poem about insects. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Poem of Language. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- —[Poem of Ohio, Kentucky, Indiana and Illinois], 1860 or before; duk.00253; xxx.00629; MS 4to 30; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  List of ideas for poems, mostly about various states. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [To the English]. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [To the English], 1860 or before; duk.00254; xxx.00110; MS 4to 30; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Ideas for a poem about various nationalities and ethnicities, suggestive of Salut au Monde! which was first published as Poem of Salutation in 1856. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with —[Poem of Ohio, Kentucky, Indiana and Illinois], and no verso image is available.
- [Poem of Fruits & Flowers], 1860 or before; duk.00255; xxx.00630; MS 4to 30; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Ideas for three different poems about various topics. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Poem of Wisconsin]. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [The carpenter's and], between 1850 and 1860; duk.00256; xxx.00631; MS 4to 30; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript containing ideas for a poem about architecture, carpentry, and masonry. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Song]. An image of the verso is not available.
- [Song], 1850–1892; duk.00257; xxx.00632; MS 4to 30; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript scrap with ideas for a poem or poems about democracy, the future, women, young men, and the joy of life. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [The carpenter's and].
- Poem [As in Visions of], 1855 or before; duk.00258; xxx.00264; MS 4to 30; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes for a poem about night "visions," possibly related to the untitled 1855 poem that Whitman eventually titled The Sleepers. Fragments of an unidentified newspaper clipping about the Puget Sound area have been pasted to the leaf. An image of the verso is not available.
- [Poem of Wisconsin], 1860 or before; duk.00308; xxx.00633; MS 4to 30; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  List of ideas for poems, mostly about various states, including an allusion to a possible "Western Edition." This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Poem of Fruits & Flowers], and an image of the verso is unavailable.
- [Theory of a Cluster of Poems], about 1860; duk.00279; xxx.00049; MS 4to 31; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Note suggesting a cluster of poems about "the passion of Woman-Love," along with a few trial lines, all apparently related to the 1860 cluster Enfans d'Adam (retitled Children of Adam in 1876 ).
- [A poem which more], 1845–1892; duk.00280; xxx.00634; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript note for a poem addressing Whitman's future readers. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Poem of the Husband].
- [Poem of the Husband], 1860 or before; duk.00281; xxx.00635; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  List of ideas for poems about "the husband," "the wife," and "marriage." This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [A poem which more].
- Religious Canticles, about 1860; duk.00282; xxx.00070; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side are notes regarding a projected group of religious poems and their significance to other Leaves of Grass poems. On the reverse is a partial draft of the 1860 poem Calamus 9, which was dropped from subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Secrets.—Secreta.
- Secrets.—Secreta, 1860 or before; duk.00283; xxx.00636; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Ideas for two poems, one listing "all the things done in secret," and the other involving a "vocabularium" of words and phrases. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Religious Canticles.
- Companions, About 1860; duk.00284; xxx.00637; MS 4to 31; prose prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Jotted idea for a series of poems about Whitman's various companions. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Poem of Young Men.
- Poem of Young Men, 1856 or before; duk.00285; xxx.00110; MS 4to 31; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript with ideas for a poem, possibly Salut Au Monde! which was first published in 1856 as Poem of Salutation. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Companions.
- An After Thought or Two, 1855 or later; duk.00286; xxx.00638; MS 4to 31; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript title, apparently for a group of poems, never used in Whitman's published work. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Poem, as in a rapt and], and [Poem ante-dating].
- [Poem, as in a rapt and], before 1860; duk.00287; xxx.00290; MS 4to 31; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript proposing ideas for a poem in the form of a prophetic vision about the future of America. Possibly related to As I Walk These Broad Majestic Days, which was first published as Chants Democratic 21 in 1860–1861. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with An After Thought or Two, and [Poem ante-dating].
- [Poem ante-dating], 1860 or before; duk.00288; xxx.00639; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript idea for a poem that would prophesy the "great results" to be had "a hundred years hence." This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with An After Thought or Two and [Poem, as in a rapt and].
- Poem L'Envoy, before 1860; duk.00289; xxx.00640; MS 4to 31; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Note for a poem. It is unclear whether this manuscript is connected to any of Whitman's published poetry. The reverse contains a fragmentary set of notes for a game of "Twenty Questions." This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Banjo Poem, Poem [?The Cruise], and [of Death—the song].
- Banjo Poem, 1845–1892; duk.00290; xxx.00641; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Scrap with just two words, apparently a trial title. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Poem L'Envoy, Poem [?The Cruise], and [of Death—the song].
- Poem [?The Cruise], 1860 or before; duk.00291; xxx.00642; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Scrap with what are apparently two trial versions of a title. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Poem L'Envoy, Banjo Poem, and [of Death—the song].
- [of Death—the song], 1845–1892; duk.00292; xxx.00643; MS 4to 31; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Idea for a poem about death, immortality, and "ensemble." It is unclear whether and how this manuscript is related to Whitman's published poetry. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with Poem L'Envoy, Banjo Poem, and Poem [?The Cruise].
- [A man of gigantic], 1855–1892; duk.00293; xxx.00048; MS 4to 32; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side is a prose fragment contemplating the combination in one man of power and compassion. The ideas and some of the phrases appear to be related to lines from the opening poem of the 1855 Leaves of Grass—what would later become section 24 of Song of Myself. The poem was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. On the reverse is another prose fragment dealing with the importance of independent thinking amid social forces of law and custom.
- Bloom, about 1856; duk.00294; xxx.00116; MS 4to 32; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Leaf made from two scraps glued together. The writing on the top scrap appears to be a note about one of Whitman's acquaintances. The bottom scrap contains notes toward Song of the Broad-Axe, which was first published in Leaves of Grass 1856 as Broad-Axe Poem before appearing under its final title in 1867.
- [What we call literature], 1860 or before; duk.00295; MS 4to 32; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Prose manuscript expressing the belief that human existence possesses a grandeur that surpasses artistic accomplishments. It is unclear whether this manuscript is related to Whitman's published poetry or prose.
- [How gladly we leave], Before or early in 1855; duk.00296; xxx.01006; MS 4to 32; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Prose fragment that characterizes social interactions with the "learned and refined" as stifling in comparison with experiences shared with "real men and women." Relationships between this manuscript and Whitman's published poetry or prose, if they exist, have not been determined.
- [Outdoors is the best], Before or early in 1855; duk.00297; xxx.01007; MS 4to 32; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Prose fragment extolling the excellence of outdoor living. It is not known whether this manuscript is related to any of Whitman's published work.
- [Remember that the clock], 1850-1855; duk.00298; xxx.01008; MS 4to 32; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Prose manuscript regarding concepts of time. It is not known to be related to any published work.
- [A poem in which is], 1856 or before; duk.00299; xxx.00052; MS 4to 33; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes for a poem about "a first-rate healthy Human Body," possibly related to I Sing the Body Electric, which was first published as the fifth poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass and substantially revised (as Poem of the Body) in 1856.
- [Remember in Scientific], 1860 or before; duk.00300; xxx.00644; MS 4to 33; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Two reminders about general principles Whitman had decided upon for future poems. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [a volume].
- [a volume], before 1860; duk.00301; xxx.00129; MS 4to 33; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Note suggesting a piece of writing to span "the whole range of recorded time," possibly related to With Antecedents, which was first published in the New-York Saturday Press ( 1860 ) as You and Me and To-day. The poem was revised as Chants Democratic. 7 in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–1861 ) and took its final title, With Antecedents, in the 1867 Leaves. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [Remember in Scientific].
- [It seems to me], 1855 or before; duk.00302; xxx.00526; MS 4to 33; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Note apparently recording Whitman's intent to eschew "ornament" in his writing, possibly related to a similar passage in the prose preface to the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [What shall the great poet be then?], [The most superb beauties], and [Make no quotations].
- [What shall the great poet be then?], 1855 or before; duk.00303; xxx.00526; MS 4to 33; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Note about "the great poet," possibly connected to a passage (denouncing the "swarms of the polished deprecating" poets) in the prose preface to the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [It seems to me], [The most superb beauties], and [Make no quotations].
- [The most superb beauties], 1855 or before; duk.00304; xxx.00048; MS 4to 33; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes, or possibly trial lines, expressing the idea that the highest beauty is found in what is "cheapest" and "commonest," possibly connected to a passage in section 14 of Song of Myself, first published untitled in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ) The poem was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves.. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [It seems to me], [What shall the great poet be then?], and [Make no quotations].
- [Make no quotations], 1855 or before; duk.00305; xxx.01009; MS 4to 33; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes, or possibly trial lines, articulating various beliefs about how to write. This scrap has been attached by a collector or archivist to a backing sheet, together with [It seems to me], [What shall the great poet be then?], and [The most superb beauties].
- [Breath and Spray], 1860 or before; duk.00306; xxx.00645; MS 4to 33; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  List of what appear to be possible titles for volumes or clusters of poems.
- [Poemet], 1860 or before; duk.00307; xxx.00937; MS 4to 33; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Lists of synonyms for "poem."
- [The Nibelungen], 1855-1865; duk.00188; xxx.00395; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  The term "Nibelungen" appears in a poem first published in the New York Truth, March 19, 1891 entitled Old Chants. The poem is one of the thiry-one poems included in Second Annex--Good-Bye My Fancy, 1891–1892.
- Preface Two Rivulets, about 1876; duk.00122; xxx.00489; MS 4to 62; poetry prose 6 leaves handwritten
  Fragment, heavily revised, of the preface to Two Rivulets ( 1876 ). Several of the leaves are made of scraps pasted together, and on the reverse of the fourth leaf is a draft fragment of the opening lines of a poem first published in the Galaxy ( September 1867 ) as A Carol of Harvest, for 1867, which was ultimately titled The Return of the Heroes, Leaves of Grass ( 1881–1882 ).
- [The name of this], between 1884 and 1888; duk.00127; xxx.00936; MS 4to 63; prose 5 leaves handwritten
  Four leaves that constitute a draft, unpublished in Whitman's lifetime, apparently of a preface to a projected volume. Also included is a note, in an unknown hand, quoting Richard Maurice Bucke's note from the posthumous publication Notes and Fragments ( 1899 ). An image for the verso of this note is unavailable.
- [(Of the great poet)], 1855 or before; duk.00128; xxx.00526; MS 4to 69; prose 3 leaves handwritten
  Notes that anticipate the preface to the first ( 1855 ) edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [Struggling steadily to the front], about 1875; duk.00129; xxx.00117; MS 4to 50; poetry 2 leaves handwritten
  Heavily revised draft of the prefatory note for Song of the Exposition, as it appeared in the 1876 volume Two Rivulets. Earlier and later publications of the poem did not include this prose introduction.
- [poet of Materialism], 1855 or before; duk.00104; xxx.00430; MS 4to 44; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript expressing a belief in the continuing "amelioration" of the earth and humankind, written on a scrap of wallpaper. Although it is cast in prose, this is probably an early draft of a group of lines, expressing similar thoughts, in Great Are the Myths, which was first published as the final, untitled, poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [In metaphysical points], 1855 or before; duk.00159; xxx.00048; MS 67; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript about the roles of science and "the soul" in the apprehension of truth. The fragmentary paragraph at the bottom of the leaf seems to be the germ of certain lines of what eventually became Song of Myself, section 23, first published untitled in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ) The poem was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves.
- [Thought], about 1860; duk.00164; MS 68; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  What appear to be draft opening lines for a poem, not known to have been published in Whitman's lifetime.
- [Produce great persons and the producers], 1856; duk.00166; xxx.00221; xxx.00113; MS 51; poetry prose 2 leaves handwritten print
  Manuscript and clipping. On one side of the manuscript leaf (see the first image linked above) are several prose notes, including two versions of a paragraph that was later revised to become a line in Poem of Many In One, published in Leaves of Grass ( 1856 ), and eventually titled By Blue Ontario's Shore. The phrase "savage and luxuriant," which appears toward the bottom of this side, was used in Whitman's open letter to Emerson, published in an appendix to the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass. On the other side of the leaf is a partial draft of Poem of The Singers, and of the Words of Poems, also first published in 1856. In the final edition of Leaves of Grass this and another poem, which had been included in every edition since 1855, were combined to form Song of the Answerer. Whitman pasted at least two newspaper clippings on the manuscript, one on each side. However, markings on both sides of the leaf indicate that Whitman potentially pasted a third, unidentified, newspaper clipping on this manuscript. One of these, which had covered Whitman's paragraphs but has since been detached, is included in the file; another is still pasted to the manuscript.
- Bunsen, 1856 or before; duk.00200; xxx.00110; poetry prose 2 leaves handwritten
  Notes on Africa. Whitman used some of the place names and a version of one of the phrases here ("The fresh-sunned Mediterranean, and from one to another of its islands") in the 1856 Poem of Salutation, which was eventually titled Salut au Monde!
- [for tramp & strike], 1879-1882; duk.00779; xxx.00539; II-7B 190; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript scrap related to Whitman's undelivered lecture The Tramp and Strike Question, which was written in 1879 but not published until it was included in Specimen Days in 1882. Although this scrap contains thoughts and ideas similar to those found in the essay, these lines do not appear to have made it into the final version of the piece. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [Chronological], 1850-1855; duk.00066; xxx.00052; prose 1 leaf, with 2 pasted-on attachments handwritten